A Guide to the Jacques J. Bronfenbrenner papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA149
Rockefeller Archive Center
Jacques J. Bronfenbrenner papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1909-1939
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bronfenbrenner, Jacques J. (Jacques Jacob)
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA149
1 Cubic Feet
1 box
Scope and Contents note
Business Manager Files.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 B788
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Medical research; Medical education; Operations management; Bronfenbrenner, Jacques J. (Jacques Jacob); Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- 1909, 1913, 2½" letter GL 6/86 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [A. Besredka] /S. Flexner. re Bronfenbrenner. In French, circa 1909
  - Exchange between Henry James and J. Bronfenbrenner re Fred Kimmer, 1913 June 16-20 1913 December 5-29
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes correspondence from June 16-20 re James objection to handling of Kimmer's departure from RIMR and outlining preferred procedures. Also includes correspondence re Kimmer's return to RIMR in 1914.
  - Bronfenbrenner/James. re lantern slides and floor plans, 1913 June 27
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, Henry James and Lee, Higginson & Co. re investments for Dr. Bronfenbrenner, 1913 October 8-December 29
- 1914 January-April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, H. James and Lee, Higginson & Co. re investments and on 7 Jan re Fred Kimmer's arrival at RIMR, 1914 January 5-8 1914 February 5-14 1914 March 5-31 1914 April 2-29
  - Exchange between H. James and Bronfenbrenner re additional staff for Bronfenbrenner, 1914 January 15-22
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner/E.B. Smith re purchase of rabbits, 1914 April 16-21
- 1914 May-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exchange between H. James, Bronfenbrenner and Lee, Higginson & Co. re investments, 1914 May 1-December 4
  - Bronfenbrenner/H. James re monkeys w/E.B. Smith reply of July 15, 1914 July 14-15
  - Bronfenbrenner/James re Theobald Smith, 1914 November 10
  - Bronfenbrenner/H. Goepper re chemist to head Chemical Dept w/7 Dec reply, 1914 December 4
- 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, H. James and Lee, Higginson & Co. re investments, 1915 April 6 1915 September 10-23 1915 October 5-6 1915 December 9-22 1916 April 20 1916 May 1-31 1916 June 3
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner and James re Effie L. MacDonald, 1915 July 8 1915 July 12
  - Bronfenbrenner/James. re Dr. Ingebrigtsen's address and employment of women from the Margaret Morrison School for Women, Pittsburgh, Pa w/Henry James reply, Sept 10, 1915 September 1
- 1917-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, James and Lee, Higginson & Co. re investments, 1917 January 11-20 1917 April 16-18 1917 September 29
    Includes: 1917 April 17. Telegram. Bronfenbrenner/James re Bronfenbrenner becoming U.S. citizen in 1914.
  - H.W. Reynolds/H. James, rereference for Bronfenbrenner's apartment rental in Brookline, Mass. w/ H. James reply, May 7, 1917 May 3
  - Bronfenbrenner/H. James, re Noguchi illness w/James reply, 17 Sept, 1917 September 14
  - Bronfenbrenner/H. James, re James resignation from RI and Bronfenbrenner investments to be handled by Mr. Greene, new RIMR Business Manager, 1918 February 16
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, H.L. Amoss and E.B. Smith, re purchase of rats and RI supplying rats to Dr. Bronfenbrenner, 1920 April 7-May 11
- 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner and S. Flexner re George De Bard, [1923] April 9-16
  - Bronfenbrenner/S. Flexner. re Bronfenbrenner's tentative appointment by RIMR, Board of Directors and Esther Greisheimer. Handwritten, [1923] May 4
  - Bronfenbrenner/L. Emmett Holt. Acknowledges appointment to RIMR from Sept 1923 - June 1925, 1923 June 20
    Handwritten.
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, Simon Flexner and E.B. Smith re arrangements for shipping to and storage of Bronfenbrenner's reprints, books, etc and care of laboratory and glassware by Jeanette McNaught, and approval of Ware Cattell, (Prof. Cattell's son) to work in Bronfenbrenner's laboratory at RIMR, 1923 August 30 1923 September 2 1924 July 1-25
  - Bronfenbrenner/S. Flexner, (copy). re Paul Kreider, R.N. Klemer, David H. Flashman and Mary Jane Hogue, 1924 August 3
    Includes Dr. Hogue's curriculum vitae.
  - Bronfenbrenner/Wm. A. White & Sons re apartment in Socony Hall, 1924 December 27
- 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bronfenbrenner/E.B. Smith re supply of media for work on bacteriophage, 1925 February 11
  - E.B. Smith/Bronfenbrenner re Ralph S. Muckenfuss appointment from 1925 June to 1926 June 20, 1925 March 10
  - Bronfenbrenner/S. Flexner and Secretary, re invitation to Bronfenbrenner by E.O. Jordan to give summer course in bacteriology at the University of Chicago w/copy of E.O. Jordan's letter, dated 21 Jan attached and S. Flexner's approval and RIMR Bd of Scientific Directors granting leave to give course, 1926 January 26-27 1926 February 9
  - Bronfenbrenner/Flexner re applicants: Dr. Bencowitz, Dr. Hetler, Dr. D.M. Grayzel, and Dr. Oscar Bodansky w/Flexner reply, 1926 May 20
  - Bronfenbrenner/S. Flexner re purchase of centrifuge and furnace w/Flexner reply, 1926 December 10
  - Bronfenbrenner/Flexner re centrifuge, Seitz filters and electric furnace w/printed flyer describing Seitz Germicide filters by Empire Laboratory Supply Co., 1926 December 15
  - Bronfenbrenner/Flexner re laboratory space at Woods Hole, 1927 January 12
  - Bronfenbrenner/E.B. Smith re laboratory space at woods Hole, outlining work to be done, 1927 April 6
  - Hennessy Realty Co. /RIMR re reference request for apartment rental by Bronfenbrenner w/E.B. Smith's reply, 1927 May 23 1927 May 25
  - Walter R. Eimer (Eimer and Amend) /RIMR re measurements and specifications of Ultra Filter designed by Bronfenbrenner, 1927 July 21
  - Bronfenbrenner/Flexner. Biographical and professional information re Bronfenbrenner w/corrections on attachments, 1928 May 28
  - E.B. Smith/Bronfenbrenner re space at Woods Hole for summer work and request for letter of resignation from RIMR by Bronfenbrenner to new appointment at Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, Mo. w/Bronfenbrenner's handwritten reply, dated June 10, 1928 June 8
  - re J.J. Bronfenbrenner's appointment as Director, Dept of Bacteriology and Immunology, Washington University School of Medicine, beginning September 1928 and RIMR gifting of special apparatus used by Bronfenbrenner to Washington University School of Medicine
    Includes.
    - St. Louis, Mo. Post Dispatch, "Washington University Names Bacteriology Head". Newspaper clipping, 1928 May 28
    - Inventory of apparatus to Washington University Medical School, 1928 June 4
    - McKim Marriott, Dean of Washington University School of Medicine/S. Flexner. Accepting gift of apparatus, 1928 June 21
    - E.B. Smith/Bronfenbrenner re May 29, St. Louis, Mb. Globe Democrat clipping, 1928 July 18
      [Clipping not in file].
- 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Exchange between E.W. Smillie and Bernard Lupinek re letter to Bronfenbrenner, 1930 February 4 1930 February 7
    [Copy of letter not in file].
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, Associated Press, E.B. Smith and Louis Schmidt, re publication of Bronfenbrenner work on bacteriophage while at RIMR, presented to Society of American Bacteriologists, at Ames, Iowa meeting of AAAS w/photograph of Bronfenbrenner, by Associated Press, 1930 February 28-March 24
  - Exchange between S. Flexner, J. Bronfenbrenner, M.S. Soule and E.B. Smith re Bronfenbrenner's presentation of a paper on bacteriophage work conducted and published at RIMR at 1930 July 20-25, Paris, 1st International Congress of Microbiology and travel grant by RIMR to assist Bronfenbrenner's travel expense to meeting, 1930 March 13-June 2
    Includes tentative program of meeting.
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, Henry S. Pritchett (TIAA), A.D. Robertson and E.B. Smith re disposal of policies under the plan of TIAA for Bronfenbrenner, 1930 May 3-12
- 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner and Bernard Lupinek re Dr. Haford relocating from St. Louis to New York to work w/Dr. Olitsky, 1936 June 8-15
  - Exchange between Bronfenbrenner, Max Theiler, W.R. Flinn and Conrad Hon re supplying Bronfenbrenner with guinea pigs from Max Theiler's special stock maintained at RI, 1939 April 20-September 29
- Financial statements/records (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bronfenbrenner financial records. In Account w/Lee, Higginson & Co., 1914 March 27 1914 March 30
  - Statements from Lee, Higginson & Co., 1915 December 15-1918 March 11
- Archives Washington University School of Medicine Library. Guide to Jacques J. Bronfenbrenner Papers, 1909-1953. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Received May, 1986.